Hi folks, today's daf is כ"ט Chaf-Tet and we actually are on
כ"ט. Chaf-Tet. We start at the very top of the line, the
two dots. So yesterday was a whole discussion about a fetus with
that was had both genitalia, androgynous or indeterminate genitalia, טומטום, tumtum, and
how the status of that both for the טומאה tumah of childbirth
and also for other הלכות, halachos, particularly זב zav and נדה niddah
and בעל קרי ba'al keri and so on. Now we go back
to the focus about the question about childbirth and we look at
the next line in the משנה, mishnah, which is when is a
fetus considered to be born? And this has a lot of relevant
הלכות halachot for, a, the הלכה halacha of טומאה tumah of childbirth,
maybe most significantly nowadays at what stage is the child born to
determine the day of the ברית? bris?
That's a very, that's probably the most relevant question nowadays and other
issues about בכור bechor and so on. So let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. The משנה mishnah had said that if it's
coming out naturally, then it's when the majority of the head, which
is the forehead, comes out. And if it's coming out, however, dismembered
or a breech baby, then there's no particular significance to the head
and then it goes by the majority of the body, when you
know when most of the body comes out. So let's take a
look. יצא מחותך ומסורס: Yatza mechutach u-mesuras: it came out dismembered or
breached or reversed. אמר רבי אליעזר: Amar Rabbi Eliezer: אפילו הראש עמהם.
afilu ha-rosh imahem. And this is probably the simple sense of the
משנה mishnah when this is even obviously by a breech the head
isn't coming out until the very end. But by a dismembered even
if the head comes out, the head has no particular significance, it's
dismembered, and it still goes by the issue of majority. אבל רבי
יוחנן אמר: Aval Rabbi Yochanan amar: רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says לא
שנו אלא שאין הראש עמהם. lo shanu ela she-ein ha-rosh imahem. No,
the case of dismembered is when the head has not come out.
אבל הראש עמהם, Aval ha-rosh imahem, but if the head is come
out, either הראש פוטר ha-rosh poter or the side is the גרסא
girsa הרי הוא כילוד, harei hu ke-yalud, it is like it is
born. So he actually says no matter what when the head comes
out it is considered born. And when the משנה mishnah says it
needs the majority, that's only when the head hasn't come out, either
because it is dismembered and it hasn't come out or because it
is a breech baby. But whatever the head comes out it's considered
born. So the גמרא Gemara says: לימא בדרב שמואל קמיפלגי? leima bi-de-rav
Shmuel kamipalgi? Let's say they argue the position of שמואל. Shmuel. דאמר
שמואל: De-amar Shmuel: אין הראש פוטר בנפלים ein ha-rosh poter bi-nefalim that
the head does not exempt by fetuses. Meaning that it
is not considered when the head comes out and it is a
fetus, not a live birth. So this is even less extreme than
the case of the משנה, mishnah, which is dismembered. It's just that
it's fetus and not a live birth. And nevertheless he says that
it's not considered to be a birth yet when the head comes
out. The only time the head is a birth according to שמואל
Shmuel is if it is a live whole birth. But if it
is a fetus,
a stillbirth, then the head does not have significance. Okay, so we
had just set a debate, which is when it's dismembered, does the
head alone make it considered born? Obviously that's worse than when it's
dead. When it's dead, at least it's the head. After the head,
it's connected to the rest of the body. The head can in
some cases more symbolize the entire child because at least it's, you
know, still connected to the child. When it's dismembered, there's more of
a reason obviously to think that the head by itself does not
make it considered like it's already born. But שמואל Shmuel goes further.
שמואל Shmuel says not even if it's dismembered, which is what the
position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was, but even if it's whole,
the fetus, as long as it's not alive, the head is not
considered make it born.
בשלמא דכולי עלמא לא פליגי. Bishlama de-chulei alma lo peligi.
No,
you know what, actually if the child is whole, nobody will disagree.
Meaning not only would they disagree, meaning everybody would argue on שמואל.
Shmuel. Normally you expect the גמרא Gemara to say actually everybody agrees
to שמואל. Shmuel. But no, everybody would argue actually when it's whole,
everybody would say and the head came out even if it's dead,
it is considered born. Everybody maybe argues on שמואל. Shmuel. כי פליגי
במחותך. Ki peligi bi-mechutach. They debate when it is dismembered. There already
there's reason to say the head by itself doesn't count. דמר סבר
בשלם הוא דקחשיב: De-mar savar bi-shalem hu de-kachashiv: when whole, as I
said, because the rest of the body is coming out and also
because it could be symbolic of the rest of the body because
it's all still one unit. בשלם הוא דקחשיב, Bi-shalem hu de-kachashiv, the
head is considered significant. במחותך לא קחשיב, Bi-mechutach lo kachashiv, not if
it's dismembered. ומר סבר מחותך נמי קחשיב: Ve-mar savar mechutach nami kachashiv:
you know what, whenever the head comes out even if it's dismembered,
it is still significant. So here you have, although the משנה mishnah
again said that when it's dismembered it goes by the majority, there's
a debate. Some want to say that that's assuming the head has
not come out. But if the head has come out, that always
is significance. So you have three positions. שמואל Shmuel who says that
even if it's attached and it's whole, as long as the child
is not alive, the head has no significance and you need the
majority. You have the next position which says no if it's whole...
whole the head had significance, but dismembered, then the head does not,
and then the third, which is the most radical, is that even
dismembered, the head is considered to be signifying that the child is
considered to be born. So that's the first way we've set up
the debate. איכא דמתני לה להא שמעתא באפי נפשה. Ika dematni la
leha shemata be'apei nafshah. Now some say this debate of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was not going on interpreting
the משנה, mishnah, whether to read the משנה mishnah that the head
had come out yet or not, but it was said independently, a
general and about a case of dismembered, but this debate was said
by itself about in just a normal הלכה halakhic question about when
is the ראש, rosh, when does the head signify that the child
is born, defined that the child is born. אמר רבי אליעזר, Amar
Rabbi Eliezer, אין הראש כרוב איברים, Ein harosh kerov evarim, the head
does not count like the majority of the limbs. ורבי יוחנן אמר,
v'Rabbi Yochanan amar, ראש כרוב איברים, Rosh kerov evarim, it does count
like the majority of the limbs. Now you cannot say obviously this
means by a live birth because we've never heard of anybody that
says in a case of a live birth you don't go by
the head. That's explicit and unanimous in the משנה, mishnah, and you
know that's never we never find that debated. So if we have
a debate here whether the head counts, it must be we're talking
not about a live birth. So here you see they are debating
in a case of a miscarriage whether the head is considered to
be like the child is born. Now notice they are not talking
about dismembered. They're just saying does the head count or not. So
that sounds to be exactly שמואל's Shmuel case: a miscarriage, not a
dismembered case, does the head count as born. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says yes, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says no. So here the גמרא
Gemara says וקמיפלגי בדרב שמואל, v'kamiflagi bed'rav Shmuel, they're debating שמואל. Shmuel.
So the difference between this version and the earlier version is that
the earlier version they were explicitly debating a dismembered case. And there
you could say that if the child is whole but just a
miscarriage, everybody would agree the head counts. Here they're not discussing the
dismembered case. Here they're just discussing does the head count. So that
seems to be that they're debating שמואל's Shmuel point. In a case
of miscarriage, does the head count. So everything fits, right, there are
basically four scenarios: normal live childbirth, everybody agrees the head counts. Okay.
Then you have whole birth but it is but it is miscarriage.
There שמואל Shmuel says it does not. Then you have dismembered birth
and the head comes out. So there רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says that doesn't count. And it's only
the position of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is the most extreme, I
guess it's not a fourth state, but the most extreme that even
in a case of dismembered, the head still signifies the whole birth
and it's considered like it's born when the head comes out. You
said something about the head in the משנה. mishnah. I told you,
we said it already and I'll repeat it for your sake because
we're saying the משנה mishnah is talking about that the head did
not come out yet. In the case where the head did come
out it would be different. I know, but then wouldn't it say,
but you know, okay I understand you know the משנה, mishnah, fine.
אמר, Amar, so איכא דמתני להא. ika dematni leha.
So now the גמרא Gemara goes on. תנן, Tenan, we taught in
a משנה, mishnah, יצא מחוטך או מסורס, Yatza mechutach o mesoras, if
the, so our משנה mishnah says if it comes out dismembered or
breech baby. Now again breech baby there's no discussion of the head
because it came out because obviously the head hasn't come out yet.
But if it came out dismembered, מי שיצא רובו הרי זה כילוד,
misheyatza rubo harei zeh keyalud, once the majority comes out it is
like it is born. So it says, so now we're obviously going
to focus on the case of מחוטך mechutach and you need majority,
head doesn't count. מדקאמר מסורס, Mideka'amar mesoras, since it says breech, מכלל
דמחוטך כתיקנו, michlal demchutach ketikno, it infers that when it's talking about
dismembered it means that it comes out in the normal order. Right?
If it's two scenarios, reverse feet first or dismembered, so presumably dismembered
means coming out in the normal order. וקאמר מי שיצא רובו הרי
זה כילוד, veka'amar misheyatza rubo harei zeh keyalud, and you still see
you need majority. So presumably, as Michael's been upset about, presumably the
case of dismembered is a case where it's coming out in the
normal order and nevertheless the head doesn't count. So קשיא לרבי יוחנן,
kashya le'Rabbi Yochanan, this is a challenge to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
who says the head always counts. So אמר לך רבי יוחנן, amar
lach Rabbi Yochanan, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say to you,
אימא יצא מחוטך ומסורס. eima yatza mechutach umesoras. No, it's one case:
dismembered and reversed. גמרא Gemara says no, והא קתני, veha katani, don't
do that. It says either, it's clear two cases. Okay fine. הכי
קאמר, hachi ka'amar, יצא מחוטך yatza mechutach if it is dismembered או
שלם o shalem or it is whole וזה וזה מסורס. vezeh vezeh
mesoras. Fine, there's two cases: there's whole reversed and there's dismembered reversed.
But either case it is reversed, it means the head has not
come out yet. Then מי שיצא רובו הרי זה כילוד. misheyatza rubo
harei zeh keyalud. So he's saying yes, the משנה mishnah does describe
whole and dismembered, but at the end of the day the משנה
mishnah is talking about scenarios where the head does not come out
first. Maybe a better way to understand this for רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is that he's giving you two reasons why the head would
not come out first. One reason is that it is breech and
the fetus is coming out first, and the other is that it
is dismembered so they're coming out in random order. But what the
point of the משנה mishnah is not that dismembering itself changes the
הלכה. halakha. The point of the משנה mishnah is when the head
does not come out first, you go by the majority of the
body. That's the way רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan reads it. Clearly it
is a forced read in the משנה. mishnah. Now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, אמר רב פפא כתנאי, Amar Rav Papa ketana'ei, this
is like a debate of תנאים. tanna'im. יצא מחוטך או מסורס, Yatza
mechutach o mesoras, if it is dismembered or breech reversed, מי שיצא
כתיקנו, misheyatza ketikno, I'm sorry it's a mistake, מי שיצא רובו, misheyatza
rubo, you go by the majority. like our משנה. Mishnah. הרי הוא
כילוד, harei hu k'yalud, it's like it's born. רבי יוסי אומר: Rebbe
Yosei omer: מששיצא כתיקנו. Misheyatza k'tikno. No, only when it comes out
normally. Now what does it mean when it comes out normally? Meaning
when it comes out breech it's not considered born? I mean that's
obviously there needs to be some context for these words. So מאי
קאמר, mai ka'amar, what is he talking about? אמר רב פפא הכי
קאמר, Amar Rav Pappa hachi ka'amar, this is what he means. יצא
מחותך ומסורס, Yatza mechutach umesuras, if it is, we're going to now
read it the way that רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan would like, if
it is dismembered and reversed as opposed to or reversed, and reversed,
מששיצא רובו הרי הוא כילוד, misheyatza rubo harei hu k'yalud, then you
go by majority. הא כתיקנו, Ha k'tikno, so implicit in the first
position is if it is the normal order, even dismembered, הראש פוטר,
harosh poter, you go by the head. So the first way of
reading it is that the implicit first position of the משנה Mishnah
is רבי יוחנן. Rebbe Yochanan. And then רבי יוסי אומר, Rebbe Yosei
omer, רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosei says, no, מששיצא רובו כתיקנו. misheyatza rubo
k'tikno. Even if it comes out in the normal order, you go
by majority. Okay, so you had a strange statement of רבי יוסי.
Rebbe Yosei. He says only when it's normal, in which it isn't
clear what is his הלכה halacha position. What does it mean only
when it's normal? And we read it to say to fit into
this debate of רבי יוחנן, Rebbe Yochanan, רבי אליעזר, Rebbe Eliezer, that
the first position is saying that you don't count the head only
when it is reversed order, and רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosei is saying
even when it's normal order you don't count the head if it
is dismembered. Okay, so that seems to be this debate. So מתקיף
לה רב זביד, Matkif lah Rav Zvid, רב זביד Rav Zvid does
not like that way of framing
the
debate. מכלל דבמסורס רובו נמי לא? Michlal d'bimesuras rubo nami lo? פוטר?
Poter? Does that you mean that when it comes out
normal
and
majority it counts, but if it is
reverse order and majority
it doesn't
count? הא קיימא לן רובו ככולו, Ha kaima lan rubo k'kulo, we
always hold the majority is like the
whole thing, so even if it's reverse order
majority would always count. Nobody ever debates that. אלא אמר רב זביד
הכי קאמר, Ela amar Rav Zvid hachi ka'amar, so
here's how to read it. And then we're basically going to say
the same thing. I mean
תוספות Tosafot tries to read it
a little differently but
we're basically going to say the same thing except a little clearer.
יצא מחותך ומסורס, Yatza mechutach umesuras,
if it is both dismembered and reversed, מששיצא רובו הרי הוא כילוד,
misheyatza rubo harei hu k'yalud, then you go by majority, meaning because
the head has not come out. הא כתיקנו, Ha k'tikno, if it
comes out normally, the head first, even dismembered, הראש פוטר, harosh poter,
the head exempts, and that would be the position of רבי יוחנן,
Rebbe Yochanan, that whenever the head comes out, whatever the case, it
exempts. רבי יוסי אומר, Rebbe Yosei omer, רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosei says,
מששיצא כתיקנו לחיים, misheyatza k'tikno l'chaim,
when it comes out naturally and it is alive. Meaning what? When
does the head matter? When it is a natural live birth. Or
maybe it means a natural non-dismembered birth. It sounds like live birth,
that would be the question of שמואל. Shmuel. But I'm willing to
tell you that now so
the head matters, meaning he's referring to the inference. The inference was
of the first position is the head always counts, and רבי יוסי
Rebbe Yosei comes back and says no, the head only counts if
it's A, normal order, it came out first, and
B, that it is a live birth. Anything less than that, the
head does not count. So that's closer to how we wanted to
say the debate. So well, right, but we're trying to make it
into this ברייתא. Baraita. So we now have again the multiple positions
of when does the head count. Everybody agrees the head counts when
it is a live birth, that might be what we just said
רבי יוסי. Rebbe Yosei. Does the head count
when it is a miscarriage but
whole? So that is
possibly what the last רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosei says, it certainly was
what רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer says, that a miscarriage whole
it counts. Does the head count if it is dismembered and totally
by itself? So there the obviously the whole weight would say that
case it doesn't count. But רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan goes so far
to say even in that extreme case the head still counts. Okay,
so that's the debate about when do we go by the head,
when do we go by the majority. As I said, the most
relevant הלכה halacha for us is ברית מילה bris milah and then
you're really dealing with live births, so most of these debates don't
matter. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. תניא נמי
הכי, Tanya nami hachi,
we taught similarly in a ברייתא. Baraita. יצא
מחותך ומסורס בפרשתא בי, Yatza mechutach umesuras b'parshata bei, whatever, if it's
dismembered and reversed, מששיצא רובו הרי זה כילוד, misheyatza rubo harei zeh
k'yalud, then you go by majority. הא כתיקנו... Ha k'tikno... no but
if it's the normal order הראש פוטר harosh poteir you go by
that even in a dismembered case even if the head is completely
detached. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yosei omeir משיצא כתיקנו לחי mishyayatza ketikno
lachai
no the only way that it is considered to be the head
is significant is when it is a natural live birth. But if
it is dismembered the head is not significant by itself. Now ואיזה
כתיקנו לחי ve'eizeh ketikno lachai and now we get finally to defining
what does the majority of the head mean? What does that mean
it comes out alive for life? משיצא רוב ראשו mishyayatza rov rosho
the majority of the head. ואיזו רוב ראשו ve'eizu rov rosho what
is that majority? רבי יוסי אומר משיצא צדעא Rabbi Yosei omeir mishyayatza
tzida
the temples. Okay if you look at רש"י Rashi right before the
משנה Mishnah you see the רש"י Rashi צדעא tzida רש"י Rashi says
temples. Okay? So there you go when the temples come out. אבא
חנן משום רבי יהושע אומר משיצא פדחתא Abba Chanan mishum Rabbi Yehoshua
omeir mishyayatza padachata the forehead which as we said although people don't
think that that's half the head it really is pro- mostly half
the face and that's the משנה. Mishnah. ויש אומרים משיצאו קרני ראשו
veyesh omrim mishyatzu karnei rosho which is
exactly what I was looking at when your horns come out when
your—so you see it's only when you're an infant that they're not
covered with hair you can see the—anyway no but רש"י Rashi says
what it means is רש"י Rashi says it means that like the
back of the I guess what we call—what do we mean when
we say crowning? Do we mean the back slope of the head?
That's what רש"י Rashi says the horns mean like the crown—isn't a
crown around? Yeah but when they say the child—the fetus crowns right?
That's a medical term. Does it mean the entire head has come
out or which part of the head? The round part. Right. So
anyway that's what רש"י Rashi says that it means like—it means like
the high part here and the back of the forehead. Okay so
that which seems actually to be to be less than—significantly less than
half the head. It certainly seems to be higher if I'm understanding
רש"י Rashi correctly higher than the forehead. Okay. So anyway that's when
the child is considered born very relevant for laws of ברית מילה.
Brit Milah. Now yes. So that's—it ends with this multi—three-way מחלוקת. machloket.
How do we פוסקן? pasken? Yeah well tough question. Like I keep
on telling you the גמרא Gemara rarely פוסקן. paskens. I mean the
גמרא Gemara is more interested in—in like—in like analyzing positions and whatever.
פסק Psaq is left up to the ראשונים Rishonim for the most
part or the גאונים. Geonim. So here as Michael indicated you know
at least one of the positions is with the משנה Mishnah there's
a סתם משנה. Stam Mishnah. So in absence of any other evidence
we'll assume you go by the סתם משנה Stam Mishnah which is
generally the assumption. Okay. So let's take a look at the next
משנה. Mishnah. המפלת hamapelet so before we had a case that we
did not know whether the child was male or female because of
the ambiguous genitalia. Now we're going to a case where it just
cannot be identified because it was a miscarriage and you just can't
inspect it or you can't see clearly enough with the fetus what
it is. So המפלת ואיני יודעת מה hamapelet ve'eini yoda'at mah so
a woman miscarries and does not know what the status of the
fetus was. Knew it was a fetus but cannot tell male or
female. תשב לזכר ולנקבה teshev lezachar ulenekeivah so she has to be
strict both ways. We've had this concept many times. Fourteen days of
טומאה tumah like a נקבה nekeivah but the טהרה taharah days end
at day forty because of the זכר zachar because you don't know
which one it is. Now איני יודעת אם ולד היה אם לאו
eini yoda'at im velad hayah im lav let's say she doesn't know.
We've had all of these משניות Mishnayot saying about things that might
not be considered a childbirth if it's not sufficiently developed if it
is misdeveloped if all these types of things strange appearances if the—if
the placenta is still with liquid and without anything that looks like
a fetus. So she really doesn't know. She didn't have any chance
to inspect the placenta to inspect what came out at all and
it might not even have constituted a fetus. So what's the הלכה?
halakha? תשב לזכר ולנקבה ולנדה teshev lezachar ulenekeivah uleniddah she has to
assume all three possible possibilities. Maybe it's a female
so that would give her two weeks of טומאה tumah but that
would give her sixty-six days of טהרה. taharah. She can't assume that
because maybe it was a male and she only has thirty-three days
of טהרה. taharah. But you know what? She can't even assume that
because maybe it wasn't a male or a female maybe she was
just a נדה niddah and she has no days of טהרה. taharah.
So she has to give herself two days of טומאה—two tumah weeks
excuse me of טומאה tumah for the assumption of a female but
afterwards no days of טהרה taharah because it's possible she was a
נדה niddah and she had no days following a טהרה. taharah. So
two days—two weeks you say. תשב לזכר ולנקבה ולנדה. teshev lezachar ulenekeivah
uleniddah. Excellent. So it could have just said לנקבה ולנדה. lenekeivah uleniddah.
זכר zachar is immaterial. The only relevance of being מחמיר machmir for
male is to limit the טהרה taharah days to forty days. But
here you're eliminating טהרה taharah days because she might not be a
יולדת yoledet at all. So the גמרא Gemara will ask why bothered
mentioning לזכר. lezachar. Okay. So let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. It could be just parallelism. It could be but the גמרא
Gemara is always interested in finding a reason. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי: amar Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi: עברה נהר והפילה avrah nahar vehipilah a woman was crossing
a river and she miscarried in the river. So this is a
scenario we've had this before a scenario to describe how it is
possible that she does not know—she has no way of inspecting what
came out. No way of inspecting the—the miscarriage. All right. מביאה קרבן
ונאכל mevia korban vene'echal she brings a קרבן. korban. She doesn't know
male or female. So fine the טומאה tumah male-female stuff but she
can assume it was a definite fetus. And therefore she would definitely
bring a קרבן korban for יולדת. yoledet. Why? Why can she assume
that? Maybe it was a— not a fetus, maybe it wasn't properly
developed, all the issues we mentioned before that would define it as
a non-fetus. Or maybe she wasn't even necessarily pregnant. Maybe something else
came out of her. How do we know? So he says הלכה
כרוב נשים. halacha kerov nashim. ברוב נשים ולד מעליא ילדן. berov nashim
velad maalya yaldan. You go after most women. Most women we can
assume when if they're pregnant, even if they miscarried, they miscarried something
which halachically qualifies as a full fetus. It's not. Now again, what
would you say if it's she's only at the beginning of a
pregnancy? It might not be fully developed. Okay, so those would be
special cases, but presumably you saw she was pregnant. So she's not
just within the first 40 days. So in those cases, a woman
who is pregnant, you assume you've got a, you know, normal fetus
developing within her that would qualify halachically for these laws, for the
requirements that we've been talking about until now. And therefore, even if
you can't inspect, you go by the majority, and you say we're
not going to worry about other possibilities. We assume it was definitely
a fetus, and therefore she brings a קרבן korban as a יולדת.
yoledes. That's what he says. Now question is how does that fit
in our משנה? mishna? Because our משנה mishna seems to consider the
possibility that maybe it was not a halachic birth. So let's take
a look. תנן. tenan. Our משנה mishna says, אינו ידוע אם ולד
הוא היה, eino yadua im velad hu haya, if she has no
way of knowing if it was a fetus because she couldn't inspect
it, which seems to be your case of the river. תשב לזכר
ולנקבה ולנדה. teshev lezachar ulenekeva ulenida. You have to be concerned that
she might not be, it might not have been a fetus at
all, and therefore she, she treated her also like a נדה. nida.
No days of טהרה. tahara. Which would mean don't eat the קרבן.
korban. You can't be certain that it was a fetus. אביי תשב
לנדה? Abaye teshev lenida? According to you why does she have to
treat herself as a possible נדה? nida? לימא הלכה כרוב נשים ורוב
נשים ולד מעליא ילדן? leima halacha kerov nashim verov nashim velad maalya
yaldan? Go after most women, and most women if they're pregnant, they,
we assume that it is a halachically defined fetus. And therefore, based
on your logic, she should not have to worry about the נדה
nida possibility, about the non-fetus possibility. So אמר מתניתין בשלא הוחזקה עוברה.
amar masnisin beshelo huchzeka ubra. Our משנה mishna is that special case
that I was telling you. You don't know she was necessarily pregnant.
You know, maybe she was, I don't know, looked, you know, she
wasn't certain whether she was pregnant or not. She, how do you
know, I mean something came out of her body, is essentially the
way it's reading. Not like a pregnant woman miscarried but you can't
identify it. It's basically reading it that this woman had some discharge
from her body. It wasn't just blood, it was something significant like
until now we've been talking about, you know, different types of masses
that are filled with things. But maybe it's without knowing that she
was really pregnant. And therefore we have to be concerned that it
wasn't a fetus. But if you knew she was pregnant, then you
do not have to be concerned about that possibility. So הכי קאמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי, hachi ka'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, what would
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi say? כשהוחזקה עוברה. keshehuchzeka
ubra. כשהוחזקה עוברה. keshehuchzeka ubra. When her, when her, you know, when
she has been established, it's known that she's pregnant. So when her
status of being pregnant is known, we assume what's developing inside of
her is a normal fetus for all halachic purposes. But if you
don't even know, and it's something that's discharged, then you have to
worry about something else. Okay, let's see if we can still maintain
this assertion that when you know pregnancy, you can assume that what
was born was a was a was a full fetus. Again, you
know, you understand this is actually a very nice, that this discussion
is coming at the towards the end of this פרק. perek. Because
we've just spent the entire פרק perek discussing things that are discharged
in different types of forms, you know, shapes of fetuses or whatever
that don't halachically count, and now we're for, to be defined as,
you know, a fetus for the purpose of birth. And now we're
saying the discussion about, okay, but you have to be concerned about
that that's ever going to happen if you don't see it. And
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi saying if you don't
see it, you don't have to be concerned about that. Okay, so
let's take a look. תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. בהמה
שיצאה מלאה ובאה ריקנית. behema sheyatza melei'a uvah reikanis. Okay, what does
that sound like, by the way? Right. Yeah, we're going to have
that phrase again by, by women, right, by רות ונעמי, Rus veNaomi,
right. אני מלאה הלכתי וריקם השיבני השם. ani melei'a halachti vereikam heshivani
Hashem. So בהמה שיצאה מלאה behema sheyatza melei'a that, that left your
sort of control when it was filled, pregnant, and it returned ריקנית.
reikanis. It returned no longer pregnant. And you weren't, you didn't see
what happened, somewhere out in the field or something it gave birth.
Okay, but obviously not a live birth. There's no calf following it.
And you want to know, do we have to assume that what,
that what came out was a halachic birth so that the next
calf will not be a בכור? bechor? That's the question. So והלכה
היא הבא אחריה בכור מספק. vehalacha hi haba achareiha bechor misafek. What
comes afterwards is a doubtful בכור bechor because maybe what came out
was not a halachic fetus like we've had discussions by humans, have
discussions by animals, and why it's not a halachic fetus and therefore,
you know, maybe it was just like a, what do you call
it? Like a placenta filled with, you know, liquid and there was
no real fetus there to constitute. And therefore maybe it's not considered
to have given birth already and the next child would be a
בכור. bechor. Okay, so that's the הלכה. halacha. You don't know. So
that seems to be a direct contradiction to רבי יהושע בן לוי,
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, because here's the case, it was clearly pregnant,
יצאה מלאה, yatza melei'a, it came back. ריקנית, reikanit, and we're still
not still can't discern with certainty that it gave birth to a
halakhic fetus. Is this Rabbi Meir then? What? Is this Rabbi Meir
who's חושש למיעוטא? choshesh lemi'uta? I guess you could say that, but
let's see what the Gemara does with it. ואמאי, ve'amai, why do
we do that? הא בהלכה כרוב בהמות ורוב בהמות ולד מעליא ילדן,
ha bahalakha kerov behemot verov behemot vlad malya yalden, according to your
logic we should assume that if you know it's pregnant, even if
we don't know what it gave birth to, it was a real
fetus and therefore the next child is not a בכור. bechor. Why
do we treat it as a ספק? safek? והא פשוט הוא veha
pashut hu and the next child should be a פשוט, pashut, meaning
a non-בכור. bechor. So אמר רבינא, amar Ravina, משום דאיכא למימר רוב
בהמות יולדות דבר הפוטר מבכורה. mishum de'ika lemeimar rov behemot yoldot davar
hapoter mibekhora. It's true, most animals that are pregnant, once they give
birth or miscarry, whatever, it is some type of a thing which
would exempt the next child from a בכור, bechor, something that would
be constitute a halakhic fetus. But however, מיעוטן יולדות דבר שאינו פוטר
מבכורה. miyutan yoldot davar she'eino poter mibekhora. There's a minority of cases
that it is not and it is some type of a placenta
filled with liquid and something that does not constitute a birth like
we've been discussing until now. Fine, that's a minority, but we're saying
we're not concerned about the minority. But here's why here we are
concerned about the minority. דכל היולדות מתנפות. dechol hayoldot mitnapfot. Any animal
that gives birth, presumably to a true fetus that counts, there's a
type of a smell after they gave birth. וזו הואיל ולא תנפה,
vezo ho'il velo tinpa, or maybe it's before though I think it's
after. No, I'm sorry, Rashi says before. Before they give birth there's
a type of smell that emits from their body. וזו הואיל ולא
תנפה, vezo ho'il velo tinpa, and this one because there was not
that smell that emitted from the body of this cow, אתרע ליה
רובא. itra lei ruba. That becomes evident, right? So basically, under normal
cases you're right, we would assume that it gave birth to a
full to a halakhic fetus. But because there's some indicators that it
was not a normal fetus. What were the indicators? It says we
didn't get this smell that normally precedes a normal type of a
childbirth. So therefore it indicated that something might be wrong or off
and therefore we have to here be concerned. And Tosafot add the
obvious point, Tosafot says look at the little Tosafot, וזו הואיל ולא
תנפה, vezo ho'il velo tinpa, וכגון שלא הייתה בהמה בחוץ דאם שהתה
אימר תנפה וילדה, ukegon shelo hayta behema bachutz de'im shehata eimar tinpa
veyalda, meaning the animal wasn't away more than a day. Right? If
the animal was away for a week, maybe it gave off that
smell, then had the miscarriage or the birth and then came back.
So it means it was in your control in a period where
if it was giving birth you would have already had that smell
and was only missing from you for a few hours or something
like that. So basically the Gemara's answer is normally we're not concerned,
but this was a special case where the absence of the smell
made us concerned that something was off and therefore we have to
be concerned that maybe it was not a normal birth. But normally
we will assume normal birth or it's funny to say this but
normal miscarriage, but you know that the fetus was normally developing and
normally therefore even without any knowledge we will not be concerned that
it was not a halakhic fetus, it was not a birth. Now
the Gemara continues, and now it gets a little complicated. כי אתא
רבין אמר, ki ata Ravin amar, when Ravin came from ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael he said, מותיב רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא תועה. motiv Rabbi
Yose berabbi Chanina to'eh. Rabbi Yose berabbi Chanina challenged Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi's position that we don't have to be concerned about a non-valid
birth. He challenged that position from a ברייתא Baraita about תועה, to'eh,
about a woman who is mistaken, does not know, is in error,
does not know exactly what her cycle is. ולא ידענא מאי תיובתיה,
velo yadana mai tiyuvteih, and I don't even understand. I don't think
it was a good question. It was then in my mind I
didn't even begin to understand what the question was. Okay, so now
what we're going to do is we're setting up the scene that
we're going to challenge Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi's statement from a ברייתא
Baraita about a woman who's in error, and then Ravin is going
to say why that wasn't a good challenge. Let's take a look
at what that ברייתא Baraita is about the woman that was in
error. מאי, mai, what'd it say? דתניא. detanya. You know you're in
trouble when the Rashis are bigger than the Tosafot. Okay. אישה, isha,
אישה שיצאה מלאה ובאה ריקנית. isha sheyatza mele'ah uva'ah reikanit. Again, a
woman went out pregnant and came back and she was no longer
pregnant. And here, והביאה לפנינו, vehevi'ah lefanenu, and what is she bringing?
She comes, she brings herself or she is actually if you want
it might actually be והובאה, vehuv'ah, she is brought, but actually I
think it's the feminine, it's not והובא, vehuv'a, והביאה. vehevi'ah. So she
brings herself, presenting herself to us. And she wants to basically say
like, okay, what is my halakhic status? Am I יולדת? yoledet? Am
I נידה? niddah? When does my cycle start? All these questions. And
basically she does not know when she miscarried. Okay? She, there was
I guess it's interesting like why doesn't she see that her stomach
is no longer sort of extended the way it used to be.
But the case is, however you understand the case, is that she
doesn't know when she miscarried. She could have miscarried today, she could
have miscarried a month ago. She just somehow maybe I don't know
who knows, maybe she was in a coma, who knows? But she
left. When she was pregnant, she comes back now, and she has
no idea when this miscarriage might have occurred. So we have to
try to figure out, number one, not only is she טמא tamei
or טהור, tahor, but the more focused question of the גמרא Gemara
is going to be: When does she go to the מקוה Mikvah
and when does she have sex with her husband? Now, I have
to tell you the assumptions that we're going to deal here. The
assumption number one is, well, really the only assumption is, that there's
a principle of בית הלל, Beit Hillel, בית שמאי Beit Shammai assuming
טבילה בזמנה מצוה, tvila bizmana mitzvah, which means, the easiest thing is
just wait until you're definitely טהור tahor and go to the מקוה
Mikvah then and be done with it. Figure out how many days.
Seven, what's the worst-case scenario? Worst-case scenario the גמרא's Gemara going to
say is, well no, worst-case scenario in terms of how טמא tamei
you are, is that you gave birth right now, that it was
a female, so it's two weeks, and the worst of that, even
worse is since you haven't been paying attention until now because we're
just assuming we have no knowledge of what happened until now. So
to add to that is that you were bleeding before you became,
before you gave birth, and you were a זבה. zava. You bled
for three days, not during your period, it wasn't with pain, if
it's with pain that discounts it, so you are what's called a
יולדת בזובה. yoledes b'zova. You're both a יולדת yoledes and you're a
זבה. zava. That's the worst case. As a זבה zava you need
seven clean days, and there's a debate: What happens during that two
weeks that you're טמא tamei for the girl if you didn't bleed
during those two days? If you were without blood, is that, could
that ever happen? Would those clean days count towards the seven days
for the זבה? zava? Okay, do you understand the question? A זבה
zava needs seven clean days. This woman is טמא tamei two weeks
without bleeding. Even if she does, if she actually doesn't, can those
count as clean days for the זבה? zava? That's a debate. That's
a question about whether ימי לידה שאינה רואה בהן, yemei leida she'eina
ro'ah bahen, days of childbirth meaning of טומאת tumas childbirth that she
is not bleeding, עולין לספירת זיבתה olin l'sfiras zivasah or not. Does
it count towards clean days for a זבה zava or not? Why?
Because they're טמא tamei days, even though there's no blood. So let's
assume that it does not. So you need two weeks for a
girl, one week of no bleeding afterwards, assuming those two weeks can't
count to the clean days of זבה, zava, one week afterwards of
no bleeding in case she's a זבה zava as well. And then
after three weeks, go to the, whatever happened, by now you're definitely
טהור, tahor, go to the מקוה, Mikvah, we're done. Okay, and that
would end the whole story. And then you can be with her
husband, end of the day. But we're going to complicate it because
we want to get exactly the first, the first moment you can
go to the מקוה. Mikvah. We're going to assume טבילה בזמנה מצוה
tvila bizmana mitzvah and that you have to, that it's a מצוה
mitzvah to go at the very first moment you're able, and then
we want to talk about all the days you have to go
in case those days are the precise day that you have to
go to the מקוה. Mikvah. So you wind up going to the
מקוה Mikvah many, many, many times. This is, yikes, this is like
a place where, you know where we say like, you know that
נידה, niddah, קינין ופתחי נידה kinin u-pischei niddah are גופי הלכה, gufei
halacha, that there's like a lot of math and a lot—these are
like the area in נידה niddah where they seem to be having
a lot of fun like trying to figure out like worst-case scenarios
and how many millions of times can you do this, assuming, again
assuming that what do you call it that טבילה בזמנה מצוה. tvila
bizmana mitzvah. Because she still can't be with her husband because it
may not be the right time, but you just have to go
just for the sake of the מצוה. mitzvah. Exactly. You go even
though you might be, because you might be טהור, tahor, but you
can't sleep with her husband because you might be טמא. tamei. You
still can't eat קדשים kodshim either. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay, so let's
take a look. We're talking about a woman who's pregnant enough so
that people saw that she was pregnant. Right. Which is, you know,
a number of months. And somehow she loses the fetus without knowing
how. No concept of what happened. Right. I know, I know. But
you know, the גמרא Gemara I think had these scenarios because it
was trying to—Look, you wouldn't know she would have had pain, she—I
mean, she had already a substantial—I know. She had to be like
more than three months showing pregnant. As we continue this case, you're
also going to see it's going to describe an extremely precise case,
you know, and she goes on and off, one week on, one
week off. I don't think it was worried about a real case.
I think it was just interested in like having fun exploring like
the permutations here. It's so much fun when you're dealing with real
women and pregnancies and right. I understand. I didn't mean funny. You
know, I sort of meant like... I know, I know. But it
does not seem like the גמרא Gemara is really believing this is
a real case. If you don't want to use the word fun,
you could use the word like, you know, illustrative. Illustrate a principle
or, you know, explore, explore the applications of the law by positing
a totally theoretical case and see how far, you know, what the
implications of the law would be. But I don't think it was
dealing with a real case. You'll see. What's the minimum amount of
time it could be? What? Minimum amount of time? Forty days. And
she's מלאה. melei'ah. But she says... yeah. All right, let's take a
look at the case. Okay. Okay, so I hear. So let's take
a look. So, שלושה שבועות טהורים ועשרה שבועות אחד טמא ואחד טהור.
Shlosha shavuot tehorim ve-asara shavuot echad tamei ve-echad tahor. So here's what
makes it very sort of special. Oh my god. So here we
go. So she is. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8,
9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. Two weeks, he's going right to
that. 11, 12, 13, 14. He's going right to that. שלושה שבועות
טהורים ועשרה שבועות אחד טמא ואחד טהור. Shlosha shavuot tehorim ve-asara shavuot
echad tamei ve-echad tahor. Okay, so I won't do anything if she's
not bleeding. She's not bleeding, she comes here. This is where she
presents herself. After three weeks. After? No, she presents herself here. Okay.
I don't know when I lost my child. I was pregnant. I
have no idea what happened in the past. Maybe I'm יולדת בזוב,
yoledet be-zav, maybe it was today, maybe it was three weeks ago,
maybe it was ten weeks ago, who knows. These three weeks she
doesn't bleed at all. Okay. Then she bleeds the entirety of every
other week. It's a very highly constructed case, okay? Right? She's bleeding
the entirety of every other week, okay, that then. When does she
go to the מקוה? mikveh? When does she have to go to
the מקוה mikveh at the precise time and when is she able
to speak with her husband? Let's first indicate where in day 40
and day 80, because day 40 and day 80 is the end
of the טהרה tahara for a boy and for a girl. Okay,
so day 40, assuming she gave birth right back then, we have
no idea what day 40 and 80 is. But assuming she gave
birth right now, okay, when is day 40 and 80? So this
is 42, right? At the end of six weeks, it's 42. So
this is day 40 and end of, yeah, this is 77, this
is day 80. Assuming that she gave birth, that the birth occurred
the day she arrived. Okay. Let's take a look at what the
הלכה halakha is. So, משמשת לאור שלושים וחמישה ומטבילין אותה תשעים וחמש
טבילות דברי בית שמאי ובית הלל אומרים שלושים וחמישה. meshamashet le-or sheloshim
va-chamisha u-matvilin otah tishim ve-chamesh tevilot divrei Beit Shammai u-Beit Hillel omrim
sheloshim va-chamisha. So she can have sex at the end of at
the day before day 35. So this is right here. This is
where she knows she's טהורה tehorah and can have sex with her
husband right in right before the last day, right at this point
she will be. Okay. Okay and she has to go to the
מקוה mikveh 95 times according to בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. So we
will see about that where you're going to get that. I mean
even if she went every single day we realize it would only
be 70, 21, 91. Okay so some days she's going to go
twice in the day and in the morning. According to בית שמאי.
Beit Shammai. Because we are assuming that she has to go to
the מקוה mikveh on the precise day she becomes טהורה tehorah and
basically according to בית שמאי Beit Shammai there are 95 possibilities of
the exact day she became טהורה. tehorah. You see, okay? She might
as well just
remain. Exactly. Exactly. ובית הלל אומרים שלושים וחמישה, U-Beit Hillel omrim sheloshim
va-chamisha, thirty-five. ורבי יוסי ורבי יהודה אומרים, Ve-Rabbi Yossi ve-Rabbi Yehuda omrim,
Rabbi Yossi and Rabbi Yehuda say, he's so sarcastic, Rabbi Yossi and
Rabbi Yehuda say דיה לטבילה שתהא באחרונה. dayah li-tvila she-tehei ba-achronah. Just
go to the מקוה mikveh at the end. Just go to the
מקוה mikveh when she knows she's טהורה. tehora. She does not have
to go precisely at the exact day or hour that she becomes
טהורה. tehor. You know there's no idea of טבילה בזמנה מצוה. tevila
bi-zmanah mitzvah. Go once when you know you're טהורה tehora and don't
worry about going before that. Now that's fine. We'll discuss all of
these. But let's first start to understand why she cannot have sex
other than starting at day here. The point is of all of
these days, the only day she can have sex in this entire
91 day period, 13 week period is this now, this 35 in
this scenario. The night before
35? Yeah,
right. Let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
בשלמא שבוע ראשונה משמשת אימור יולדת זכר היא. Bishlama shavua rishona meshamashet
eimur yoledet zachar hi. שניה אימור יולדת נקבה היא. Shniya eimur yoledet
nekeiva hi. So why can she not have sex here? Because this
might be, right, this is a possible טומאת יולדת, tumat yoledet, right?
Right? So obviously all I had to say is the type she
birthed but then just throw in. Even for a boy this would
be off. Okay so she's טמאה tmeia for a girl next so
those days she's טמאה. tmeia. So she has to assume she's טמאה
tmeia those. Okay.
אלא שבוע שלישי אימור יולדת נקבה וזבה היא. Ela shavua shlishi eimur
yoledet nekeiva ve-zava hi. This is what I told you. This maybe
she's a זבה. zava. So if she's a זבה zava and you...
you cannot count these days even though there is no bleeding, right,
bleeding only starts here. Okay. But since זבה, zavah, if you cannot
count these days, why? Because we would say ימי לידה שאינה רואה
בהם
אינם עולים לטבילה דידה. yemei leida she-eina roah bahem einam olim le-tvila
didah. That's the phrase.
Catchy phrase. Why are you using it as a conversational... I don't
know.
So, so these cannot count for שבעה נקיים. shiva neki'im. So this
is her ז' נקיים zayin neki'im and plus she's still if she's
a זבה. zavah. So she became a זבה zavah back here, three
days of bleeding off of her cycle. So these are the two
weeks of a יולדת. yoledet. These can't count towards towards the seven
if you rule that way, the בית דין, Beis Din, if you
rule that way they can't count towards the seven. Now she's still
טמאה t'meiah of זבה, zavah, she waits seven days. Okay. Ha! So
you would say great, so go to the מקוה mikvah this night.
Okay, there's a little bit of a problem. Is that that night
she started bleeding? Because the גמרא Gemara is going to say that
the bleeding that started in week four started at the night. The
bleeding was not in the daytime but at the night. So imagine,
they had higher clean days and that שבת Shabbos was the last
day of the week, right? שבת Shabbos was her seventh day of
being of clean days of a זבה, zavah, all ready to go
to the מקוה mikvah Saturday night, beginning of week four, and she
bleeds. So she can't go to the מקוה mikvah here, in this
constructed scenario. Okay. So there's going to be a question why couldn't
she go to the מקוה mikvah because a זבה zavah could go
to the מקוה mikvah in the daytime doesn't have to wait till
the night? But let's wrap it up now. So she bleeds this
entire period. Okay. So what happens, she bleeds this entire period? She
is a נדה. niddah. But not necessarily a נדה niddah because she
might be a זבה, zavah, right? So if...
how would she be a זבה? zavah? Wait a minute. Did she
have a נדה niddah period? No, no, no. This is the first
bleeding that she had.
She didn't bleed at all here. Oh,
wait a minute, oh no, no. The reason she might be, here's
why she... here's why, here's why she might be a זבה. zavah.
She might be a זבה zavah
because would she just be a נדה niddah there? No, no, no.
Take a look why can't... why can't she have sex during this
bleeding? Okay.
Oh, hold on a second. Her ימי טהרה yemei tahara end sometime
soon. Hold on.
No, no, no. It's not because she's a זבה. zavah. Because I'll
tell you why I'm thinking this, wait a minute. A woman can
only be a זבה zavah within
days 8 through 18, 19 after she became a נדה. niddah. So
you can't have a זבה zavah without there having been a relatively
recent bleeding of a נדה. niddah. Since she didn't bleed here at
all, how was she a זבה? zavah? How'd she do it when
she was pregnant? Because
she bled here and then she bled again. So the first bleeding
back here made her a נדה niddah and these days of bleeding
made her a זבה, zavah, and that was prior to conception. Oh,
she was pregnant, all while she was pregnant. We don't know what
her past history was. But here she cannot become a זבה. zavah.
A woman cannot be a זבה zavah unless she's bled relatively recently
in the past and been a נדה. niddah. But the reason here
she cannot be טהורה tehorah here is because maybe her ימי טהרה
yemei tahara went up to this point. Okay. Maybe six out of
those seven days that blood didn't count. Why would the blood not
count? Because maybe that was within the 40 days or the 80
days of טהרה tahara of being a יולדת yoledet with the תוספות
Tosafos and the פלפול. pilpul. Are you with me here or no?
If, let me tell you, if she became a נדה niddah here
at the beginning of week four, when does her נדה niddah period
end? At the end of week... at the end of week four,
go to the מקוה, mikvah, be with her husband. But let's say
of these days in week four, א, ב, ג, ד, ה, ו,
ז, alef, beis, gimmel, dalet, hei, vav, zayin, of these days of
the week, let's assume that the first six of them were part
of the 40 days or the 80 days of childbirth. So that
doesn't make her a נדה. niddah. Her נדה niddah period didn't start
here. That was bleeding during the 40 or the 80 days. We
don't know when those 40 or 80 days begin or end, right?
We don't know when she began, when her childbirth took place. Yes?
So therefore if she bled on day seven, is that
where we assume it starts at day
zero? Wait, it might have started back here. Oh, we're trying... and
if it started back here, this 40 is when it's definitely over.
But it might be over sooner. So if it's over here, none
of... her נדה niddah did not start, her נדה niddah started here.
Okay. And therefore since her נדה niddah started here, it goes all
the way up to Friday. And therefore the only day she can
now go to the מקוה mikvah
is Friday night, night before the 35th and that is the only
day she could go to the מקוה. mikvah. Are you with me?
Now why can
she
not repeat the same thing here? Why
can't you say go to the מקוה mikvah then here, like this
is the day and go to the מקוה mikvah here? So what's
the answer? Because... because the 40 days might be over.
Definitely over. Yeah but the 80, the
80, why can't she again go to the מקוה mikvah here? Meaning
why did he repeat this idea? Worst case scenario she's a נדה
niddah on the last day, she is a זבה zavah here. She's
a זבה, zavah, right? Here, if this was her נדה, niddah, right?
And then, then this bleeding over here, the bleeding anywhere
between 80 to 90. So if this was נדה niddah blood, then
this repeat bleeding makes her a זבה. zavah. So by the time
you're already here, this could make her a זבה zavah and then
you need seven clean days. Not two days, you need seven. And
then she might be, maybe she's a זבה, zavah, another seven days.
Maybe this is her זבה, zavah, another seven days. This could go
on forever, right? Right. Okay. Okay? So anyway, you could get a
lot more than 95 then. I'm not sure. I'll have to think.
Because after a while it can't go on because after a while
the, I don't know, it might stop at some point. Anyway, let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. So it says like
this, אלא
שבוע רביעי, Ella Shavuah Revi'i, back to week four. אף על גב
דקחזיא דם תשמש דם טהור. Af al gav deka hazya dam tishamesh
dam tahor. He says, look, why don't we just assume? Forget it.
How, this is basically what James's question was. If we assume it
starts here—now we don't know, but if we assume it starts here—then
it's definitely in your 40 days, right? Why not have sex this
week? Okay? Who cares about the blood? You're definitely in your 40
days if we're assuming that the birth began here. That's the question.
Why not have sex here? It's definitely דם טהור. dam tahor. Okay?
So where were we?
לאו משום—so Lav mishum why don't you have sex during that week
four? משום דלא חזינא בתר רובא. Mishum delo hazina batar ruba. It
must be, this is, all of this was brought in to challenge
the idea that we always assume, except with knowledge, that the woman's
birth was a הלכתית halachic birth, was a, you know, that the
fetus was counted and so on. So he says, I will tell
you the reason you're not counting this. The reason you're not counting
this is you don't know she had ימי טוהר. yemei tohar. How
do you not know she had ימי טוהר? yemei tohar? Because maybe
the miscarriage—maybe it wasn't an actual הלכתית halachic fetus? And therefore, that's
why, but if you hold like רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi, that you always assume there was a הלכתית halachic fetus,
then you would have had ימי טוהר yemei tohar and week four
would have not been a problem. That was the challenge for
רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. Look, what's the matter
with week four during ימי טוהר? yemei tohar? It must be that
we can't assume ימי טוהר. yemei tohar. We don't know that the
fetus was a... Because this is a whole strange case to begin
with. Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is answering. That's what it
says, אלא מאי לא ידענא מאי תיובתיה. Ella mai lo yadana mai
tiyuvtei. So what did רבי Rabbi mean when he says I don't
even begin to understand the question? אימר הרחיקה לידתה. Eimar hirchika leidatah.
So
maybe because it has nothing to do with assuming it's not a
valid birth. We totally assume it was a valid birth, we totally
assume you have 40 days. We just don't know when the 40
days
begin. אימר הרחיקה לידתה, Eimar hirchika leidatah, maybe her birth occurred way
back here. So maybe the problem here, meaning not having sex during
this week, is not because that it might not have been a
total a good childbirth. It was totally a הלכתית halachic childbirth. It
just might have started way back here. And by the time you
get here, the 40 days are up. Okay? So that's the focus
of why this is being brought in. Now we get the fun
of further analyzing this. But the reason this was brought in was
because it says why is this blood a problem if she miscarried?
It must be we're not sure that it counts as a miscarriage,
we're not sure it was a fetus. And the answer is no.
The reason the blood is a problem is we don't know when
she miscarried. She might have miscarried way back here and by the
time you get here the 40 days are up. Okay? Is that
clear what the purpose of that was? Okay. Now let's continue. Now
that we've dealt with how that was or was not a question
to the idea that you can't assume miscarriage, you can't assume like
a fetus, let's take a look at how we understand this whole
thing. So
back to this idea. השבוע חמישי דטהור תשמש. Hashavuah chamishi detahor tishamesh.
So I don't get it, says the גמרא. Gemara. This week, as
we were saying, why not have sex the whole week? Let you
be a נדה niddah here and fine and then go to the
מקוה mikvah here and have sex this whole week. Why not?
So it says
because השבוע רביעי כל יומא ויומא מספקינן בסוף לידה בתחילת נדה, Hashavuah
revi'i kol yoma veyoma maspikinan besof leidah betichilat niddah, like I said
to you, because the week four we don't know any day might
have been the last day of the 40 days of לידה. leidah.
Okay, of the 40 days of טהרה. taharah. So her נדה niddah
period did not necessarily start on Sunday. Maybe all of these days
were still within the 40 and her נדה niddah began on שבת.
Shabbat. And therefore she remains נדה niddah through Friday. Okay? And that's
the worst case scenario. ובעשרים ותמני גופא Uve'esrim vetamni gufa and on
day 28 itself, right, the last day of week four, the שבת,
Shabbat, אימר תחילת נדה היא, eimar tichilat niddah hi, so the worst
case scenario... בסוף *Besof* of the עשרים ושמונה גופא *esrim v'shmoneh gufah*,
and on day 28 itself, right, the last day of week four,
the שבת *Shabbos*, אמר תחילת נדה היא *amar techilas niddah hi*, so
the worst-case scenario is the שבת *Shabbos* of week four. That was
the first day out of the 40, and that was the day
the נדה *Niddah* began, and it goes through the Friday of week
five. ובעי למיסב שבעה לנידותה *U'va'i l'misab shiva l'niddusa* and he has
to make seven days till the שבת *Shabbos* of week five while
she is a
נדה *Niddah*. ובכ״א תשמש tashmesh. *esrim b'chad tishamesh* and therefore on so
and on twenty-one oh so okay fine. So that explains how we
get to have to go to the מקוה *mikvah* here, and as
I told you afterwards, then the question becomes now she's a זבה
zavah *zavah*, maybe because of this bleeding she's a זבה zavah *zavah*
here, seven clean, and that accounts how come after that it's all
off. So this gets us how this is the one day out
of this entire very highly constructed scenario that he can actually have
sex with her husband. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says wait, I
have another day. Which is that day? ובכ״א תשמש
*esrim b'chad tishamesh*. How about day 21? How about remember she was
this week here that she wasn't bleeding and we were saying were
the שבעה נקיים *shivah nekiyim* right of week three were the שבעה
נקיים *shivah nekiyim* in case she was a זבה zavah *zavah*. Now
a זבה zavah *zavah* counts seven clean days and goes to the
מקוה *mikvah*, anybody knows when? On the seventh day. On the seventh
day during the day itself, based on the principle of מקצת היום
ככולו *miktzas hayom k'kulo*. And then she's a טבולת יום *tevulas yom*
so she can have sex. Okay. So a זבה zavah *zavah*, I
mean nowadays also women go to the מקוה *mikvah* at night, and
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says why don't they go to the מקוה
*mikvah* in the day? Women nowadays are somewhat like זבות *zavos*, we'll
discuss all that later. But according to הלכה *halacha*, a sort of
like you know a זבה zavah *zavah* goes to the מקוה *mikvah*
on the beginning of day seven she came and therefore she's טהורה
*tehorah* because of מקצת היום ככולו *miktzas hayom k'kulo*. So says the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
and he can have sex with her husband. Here on the שבת
*Shabbos* which is the day seven of the שבעה נקיים *shivah nekiyim*,
go to the מקוה *mikvah* שבת *Shabbos* day and if I don't
bleed at night so the next week will be you won't be
the rest of the week will be no good but at least
here שבת *Shabbos* day she should be able to be having sex
with her husband. That's at least the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s source for
people going water on שבת *Shabbos*. Well, that's a different question about
טבילה בזמנה מצוה *tevilah bizmanah mitzvah* whatever.
Women go to the מקוה *mikvah* on שבת *Shabbos* all the time.
Anyway so the גמרא *Gemara* says
here's the answer. רבי שמעון היא *Rabbi Shimon hi*. This is רבי
שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* דאמר אסור לעשות כן שמא תבוא לידי ספק *d'amar
assur la'asos kein shema tavo lidei safek*. That you're not allowed to
do that because it leads to doubt. What does that mean? So
it means that רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* did not like the idea,
there's a whole debate of ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim* maybe the חכמים *Chachamim*
agree with רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. What is he talking about? But
anyway רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* did not like the idea of a
זבה zavah *zavah* going to the מקוה *mikvah* on day seven and
having sex while it was still day seven. Why? Because day seven,
the reason you can go to the מקוה *mikvah* the morning of
day seven although you need seven full days is the principle of
מקצת היום ככולו *miktzas hayom k'kulo*, part counts as all. But because
it's based on part counts as all, let's say at the end
of the day the all didn't work out. Let's say she bled
towards the end of day seven after having gone to the מקוה
*mikvah*. We wouldn't say it's a new טומאה tumah *tumah*, we would
say the only reason we counted the morning of day seven is
because it was it was it represented the whole. But at the
end now that we see you bled later, that morning going to
the מקוה *mikvah* didn't count because now that whole day was a
טמא *tamei* day. So if a woman bleeds on the same day
after going to the מקוה *mikvah* of day seven of a זבה
zavah. *zavah*, then she was טמאה *temeah* consistent straight. The מקוה *mikvah*
didn't count. So therefore so therefore רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says I
don't want you to go to the מקוה *mikvah* on day seven,
or at least he's saying if you do go to the מקוה
*mikvah* I don't want you to have sex. There's מחלוקת ראשונים *machlokes
Rishonim* which is he out which is he discouraging. Is he going
to the מקוה *mikvah* or having sex? But either way certainly minimally
I don't want you to have sex after having gone to the
מקוה *mikvah* on day seven because might be that later you'll bleed
and retroactively you'll have had been having sex באיסור *b'issur*. So can
the woman go to the מקוה *mikvah* on שבת *Shabbos* day here?
Yes, but according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* at least she shouldn't
be having sex because maybe she'll bleed later and therefore and then
she'll have been a זבה zavah *zavah* the whole time and therefore
that is not a day that she can be having sex. Some
say רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says she can't even go to the
מקוה *mikvah* but minimally she can't during the day she has to
wait until night but minimally she can't have sex if she did
go during the day. Yes, it reminds me a little of the
first מחלוקת *machlokes* in מסכתא *masechta* about you discover that you were
bleeding, she discovered she's bleeding and how long ago it was, maybe
that retroactively made her טמאה *temeah* and so forth. Right, although there
it's a question about when she began bleeding, here it's a question
that she definitely bled. We didn't have to say she maybe was
bleeding in the morning. Yes, we know you bled at 4:00 PM.
But if you bleed at 4:00 PM, you can't count day seven
towards your seven clean days and even though you went to the
מקוה *mikvah* at the beginning of day seven it's only because you
counted all of day seven to your credit. Now that you bled
at 4:00 PM day seven doesn't count and you didn't have seven
clean days. That's the logic, not because maybe you bled. But that's
according to everybody, so why would so you make it sound like
it's just רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* for everybody. Yeah maybe after seven
clean days we're not חושש *choshesh* for that you know and we
mean if she bled she wouldn't be זבה zavah, *zavah*. No, they
agree with the principle, the question is how much does that lead
you to say don't do it because something might happen to be
חושש *choshesh* for that possibility. Is that a דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* for that?
You know that's an interesting question. The answer is probably yes, I
mean in the sense that what stage. consider it an אונס and
not a שוגג. shogeg. So but anyway, but certainly possibly. Okay, now
the גמרא says we're not done, let's have another scenario. Okay, or
say she'll תשמש. Okay, okay says the גמרא, but at least here
Saturday night have sex. Because presumably she didn't bleed till Sunday morning.
Have sex Saturday night of this week three. So the גמרא says
no. Why not? It says כשראתה בערב. kshe-ra'ata ba-erev. I already told
you the answer to that. We're assuming she's bleeding in not in
the daytime but in the nighttime. So she's going to bleed here
Saturday night. So though Saturday night her זבה zavah. period is over,
assuming she's a זבה zavah and she's waited to go to מקווה,
mikvah, waited to have sex, she doesn't have a chance to have
sex because she bled right away when it became Saturday night.
So the גמרא says ומטבילין אותה. u-matbilin ota. Now we get down,
finally now we figured out why in this entire thing she's only
having sex once. Now we have to figure out how she gets
ninety-five times to go to the מקווה mikvah according to בית שמאי.
Beit Shammai. ומטבילין אותה תשעים וחמש טבילה, u-matbilin ota tishim ve-chamesh tevillah,
ninety-five times. שבוע קמא מטבילין אותה בלילותא אם ילדת זכר היא. shavu'a
kama matbilin ota ba-leilusa im yeledet zachar hi. Okay,
so the first week, meaning here's the point, she's going to go
to the מקווה mikvah at night assuming she is a נידה niddah
or a יולדת, yoledet, because a נידה niddah and יולדת yoledet go
to the מקווה mikvah at night. She might have to go to
the מקווה mikvah in the day assuming she was a זבה zavah
and her seven clean days were up, okay, because a זבה we
said would go in the day, which by the way means simply
what ראשונים just say don't have sex but he still's saying go
to the מקווה mikvah during the day. Okay, so this week we
only begin to be concerned about a זבה after the third week.
Okay, so this week, if actually no, I don't know, anyway here
she's going to go seven times, why? Because she might have given
birth back here and any one of these days might be the
last day of childbirth, right? And therefore all the way here she's
going seven times at night because she might have given childbirth here
and then this day will be the last day of childbirth for
a girl and any time prior so that any other night prior
right would have been the last night of childbirth of the fourteen
or of the week, so she's going all of those nights. So
that's fourteen nights.
אם ילדת זכר. im yeledet zachar. So the first week is because
of a male, could be a female but
backup. שבוע שני מטבילין אותה בלילותא אם ילדת נקבה היא. shavu'a sheni
matbilin ota ba-leilusa im yeledet nekevah hi. It was a female, but
but maybe it could be a female that had was having birth
a week or two ago. So any of those fourteen nights first
could be the last night of the of the seven or fourteen
days of childbirth and she would go to the מקווה. mikvah. ביממא,
bi-yemama, in the day, אם ילדת זכר בזיבי. im yeledet zachar be-zovi.
See in the first right now this is the no no no
yeah right, so here, okay,
in this case right, if this is we are assuming that if
she had clean days prior they don't count. There's a question about
that you need to might need
ספורים לפנינו, seforim lefaneinu, you might have to like you know know
that you're counting for your seven clean days and observe that they're
clean in order for it to count. So it is not possible
that she if she was a זבה it's not possible she finished
any earlier than this week. Okay? Because this was the first week
we saw she saw that was totally clean. Times she saw that
was totally clean. So for a זבה this week does not count.
But this week, since it's all clean, she's seen seven clean days,
any one of these days could be the last day of her
of her seven clean days of being a זבה. Do you get
it? Meaning if she if she was a if she was a
זבה and you had a week of the end of her being
the טומאה of a זבה, then this worth her second clean days
and she goes here. If however one anyway if it was one
you'll figure it out but anyway any of those days could be
the last these seven days or any other type any seven days
starting from here, any group of seven days could have been the
seven clean days of a זבה. So she goes fourteen times in
the morning. So all of these mornings she have to go as
well. So this is seven nights and seven days. Okay so there's
the twenty-one times. Now we're up to twenty-one and we'll just and
wait a minute we'll just read to the end of it, we're
not done believe me. Okay so שבוע שלישי shavu'a shelishi that's the
second week, שבוע שלישי מטבילין אותה ביממא אם ילדת נקבה בזיבי. shavu'a
shelishi matbilin ota bi-yemama im yeledet nekevah be-zovi. Okay and and now
and so here obviously it's going to be seven clean days seven
days for the same reason that this might have been the week
of becoming a non-זבה sorry this could this could have been the
seven clean days and then she goes here here here you know
and any one of these could have been the groups of the
seven clean days, so the seven days of a זבה could have
ended at any of the days of this week and you have
the seven days. Okay so now we're at twenty-eight. Okay so and
we will continue this tomorrow we'll find out how how we get
to ninety-five. Only thirty-five. No we haven't figured out the nights of
this yet. To be continued.